{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man became greatly angry when he found his firstborn had slept with his concubine Bilhah. He gradually claimed the majority of his uncle’s flock of sheep and goats and married two of his daughters. This man was born grabbing the heel of his twin brother, a redheaded hunter who was tricked into bequeathing his birthright to his man. For ten points, name this son of Isaac whose descendants formed the tribes of Israel.",
      "answer": [
        "Jacob",
        "Israel until mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Two Penny Act established that ministers be paid two pennies per pound of this commodity, a move which led to Parson’s Cause. William Cunningham was part of a group of Glasgow merchants known as the “lords” of this commodity. The Orinoco variety of this crop dominated Chesapeake Bay, which was known as “this crop’s” coast. John Rolfe introduced this crop to Jamestown. For ten points, name this cash crop, used in the production of cigarettes.",
      "answer": "tobacco"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man besieged a city after a revolt by Ibn Jahhaf killed the city’s ruler, al-Qadir. After defeat at the Battle of Sagrajas [sah-grah-has], Alfonso VI recalled this man from exile to command his armies. Sancho II of Castile made this man his standard-bearer and allowed him to command the expedition against Zaragoza. This man established an independent state based at Valencia after defeating the Almoravid Berbers during the Reconquista. For ten points, name this national hero of Spain.",
      "answer": [
        "El Cid or Rodrigo D´ıaz de Vivar",
        "El Campeador"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Ken Khachigian, this President’s chief speechwriter, penned an apology speech for this man to deliver at Bergen-Belsen following his involvement in the Bitburg controversy. This man’s doctor replied “Today, Mr. President, we are all Republicans” after he survived an assassination attempt conducted by John Hinckley. This former President of the Screen Actors’ Guild was succeeded in office by his Vice President, George H.W. Bush. For ten points, name this conservative U.S. President who led during much of the 1980s.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people established a kingdom centered around Toulouse until they were forced out of France in the Battle of Vouille. The execution of the general Stilicho allowed these people to win a war against the weakened forces of Honorius. The emperor Valens was slain at Adrianople fighting against these people, who sacked Rome in 410 AD under the rule of Alaric. For ten points, name these Germanic peoples whose name implies that they came from the West.",
      "answer": "Visigoths"
    },
    {
      "question": "A month-long hearing in 1954 ended with this man losing his security clearance due to claims, by William Borden, of Communist ties. This man chose Norris Bradbury to replace him as Director of a laboratory that he left in 1945. This man pondered a quote from the Baghavad Gita, “Now I am become Death, the destroyer of worlds,” at the successful Trinity test. For ten points, name this head of the Los Alamos lab during World War II’s Manhattan Project.",
      "answer": "Julius Robert Oppenheimer"
    },
    {
      "question": "This was the surname of the most recent Vice President to die in office, a man known as “Sunny Jim,” as well as the surname of a Treasury Secretary known as the “Ohio Icicle.” In 1884, a man with this surname said “I will not accept if nominated and will not serve if elected.” That man, a former Civil War general, was the brother of John, whose 1890 law was used to break up Standard Oil in 1911. For ten points, give this surname of an Ohio Senator who sponsored an early Antitrust Act and of General William Tecumseh.",
      "answer": [
        "Sherman",
        "James Sherman, John Sherman, William Tecumseh Sherman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Rain and this resource were mythologically provided to Wagadu by a black snake called Bida until a young man cut off its head. The “silent trade” often exchanged salt for this resource, which names an African colony that gained independence from Britain in 1957. When Mansa Musa traveled the Hajj, he distributed so much of this resource in Cairo that its prices remained depressed for many years. For ten points, name this precious metal once mined in the soil of Ghana.",
      "answer": "gold"
    },
    {
      "question": "One work by this artist shows a man being attacked by owl-like demons, part of his Los Caprichos series. This artist created a series of etchings of gruesome scenes following Napoleon’s invasion of his home country in the Peninsular War. In his old age, this artist began a series of paintings on the walls of his home, including one of Saturn Devouring His Son. For ten points, name this Spanish artist who painted an execution scene in The Third of May, 1808.",
      "answer": "Francisco Goya"
    },
    {
      "question": "Finland is investigating claims that Rami Adham, this city’s “toy smuggler,” has misused charity donations. Fighting in this city has destroyed parts of the Al-Madina Souq district. Omar Daqneesh was photographed sitting in an ambulance after surviving an air strike in this city. In an interview on MSNBC, Libertarian Party candidate Gary Johnson was widely mocked after asking “What is [this city]?” For ten points, name this city in northern Syria, its most populous prior to the Syrian Civil War.",
      "answer": "Aleppo or Halab"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A group created to perform this action was founded by Abraham Woodhull, who used the name Samuel Culper. While performing this action, Robert Townsend discovered a shipment of paper that British printers intended to turn into counterfeit bills. After being arrested while performing this action, one man stated “I regret I have but one life to lose for my country.” A “tailor’s apprentice” performs this action in the musical Hamilton. For ten points, name this action performed by Nathan Hale with the goal of reporting British troop movements.",
        "answer": "spying for the United States"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another member of the Culper Ring was this man, a “spy on the inside” according to the musical Hamilton. This New York-based tailor used his slave Cato to smuggle information to George Washington.",
        "answer": "Hercules Mulligan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Eighty-four pianists performed this piece simultaneously at the opening ceremonies of the 1984 Olympics. Though this piece was orchestrated four times by the composer of the Grand Canyon Suite, Ferde Grofe, its opening was improvised by Ross Gorman. This piece was premiered at a concert, styled “An Experiment in Modern Music,” at Aeolian Hall by Paul Whiteman’s band. A 17-note clarinet glissando open, for ten points, what fusion of jazz and classical forms for piano and orchestra, composed by George Gershwin and given a colorful name?",
        "answer": "Rhapsody in Blue"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The inspiration for Rhapsody in Blue came to Gershwin while he was using this form of travel. A Billy Strayhorn jazz standard popularized by Duke Ellington informs you that, to get to Sugar Hill way up in Harlem, you must use this form of travel.",
        "answer": "train ride"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Gay survived this battle, the only member of Torpedo Squadron Eight to do so. Dauntless dive bombers were used at this battle, in which the Mikuma and Akagi were lost. The naval code JN-25 was broken shortly before this battle, in which the Hornet and Enterprise provided air support. The Yorktown and four Japanese carriers were sunk in, for ten points, what 1942 battle, considered to be the turning point in the Pacific theater of World War II?",
        "answer": "Battle of Midway"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This admiral was the Japanese commander at Midway and had earlier planned the Pearl Harbor attacks. Less than a year after Midway, this man was killed when his plane was shot down in Operation Vengeance.",
        "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, vassals pleged themselves to their lords through contracts called manrents. One leader of this kingdom lost the Battle of Falkirk after his schiltron formations proved useless against archers and joined with Andrew Moray to win the Battle of Stirling Bridge. Edward Longshanks executed this country’s national hero, William Wallace, in 1305 during its war for independence. For ten points, name this country that signed the 1706 Treaty of Union to join with its southern neighbor, England.",
        "answer": "Scotland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This king of Scotland defeated Edward II’s much larger army at the Battle of Bannockburn during the First War of Scottish Independence.",
        "answer": "Robert the Bruce or Robert I of Scotland"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was ruled by a council of nine men called the Signoria, headed by a Gonfaloniere of Justice. In the Battle of Montaperti, Siena’s Ghibellines defeated this city’s Guelphs. Supporters of the Pope plotted the Pazzi Conspiracy to overthrow this city’s ruling family. Valuable objects were burned by a preacher from this city, Savonarola, during the Bonfire of the Vanities. This city’s rulers included Cosimo the Great, who used his banking wealth to sponsor artists like Donatello. For ten points, name this center of the Renaissance, an Italian city ruled by the Medici.",
        "answer": "Florence"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Florentine ruler, known as “the Magnificent,” survived the Pazzi Conspiracy and invited Savonarola to Florence.",
        "answer": "Lorenzo de’Medici or Lorenzo the Magnificent"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, 15,000 soldiers deliberately slowed their pace to capture a castle garrisoned by only 500 troops, thus securing victory for a clan in a 1600 battle. The motto “enrich the country, strengthen the military” was used by a government in this nation to promote industrialization; that government put down the Satsuma Rebellion. For ten points, name this imperial Asian nation which underwent the Meiji Restoration.",
        "answer": "Japan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This class of samurai warriors lacked a lord or master during Japan’s feudal period. 47 of these figures notoriously avenged the death of their master in the 18th century.",
        "answer": "ronin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A former hotel in this state, the Royal Poinciana, was once the largest wooden building in the world. A city in this state became the largest by area in the contiguous USA when it consolidated with Duval County in 1968. A railroad along this state’s eastern coast was developed by Henry Flagler; that railway’s southernmost portion is now the Overseas Highway to Key West. For ten points, name this southern state, home to Jacksonville and Miami.",
        "answer": "Florida"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Florida city, established by Spanish settlers in 1565, is the oldest continuously- occupied European settlement in the continental US.",
        "answer": "St. Augustine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A poem addressed to this person imagines “A crown, a mansion, and a throne that shine, / With gold unfading” and begins by describing a “Celestial choir! enthron’d in realms of light.” An anecdote-filled biography of this man was written by Parson Weems in 1800; that biography claims that, at the age of six, this man could not tell a lie when asked if he cut down a cherry tree. For ten points, name this first president of the United States.",
        "answer": [
          "George Washington",
          "“To His Excellency General Washington”"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The poem “His Excellency General Washington” was written by which early female African- American poet?",
        "answer": "Phyllis Wheatley"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "surname will only get you prompted. Who...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about surname will only get you prompted. Who......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Re-married Aristotle Onassis after the assassination of her husband, John?",
          "answer": [
            "Jacqueline or “Jackie” Bouvier Kennedy Onassis",
            "any",
            "all underlined parts"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaigned for Hillary Clinton and campaigned against child obesity over the last eight years?",
          "answer": "Michelle Robinson Obama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote “Remember the ladies” in a letter to her husband, John, in 1776.",
          "answer": "Abigail Smith Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saved a picture of George Washington when the British burned the White House?",
          "answer": "Dolley Payne Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffered the loss of her son Tad 6 years after her husband was assassinated?",
          "answer": "Mary Todd Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pushed for highway beautification in the 1960s?",
          "answer": [
            "Claudia Taylor Johnson",
            "Lady Bird Johnson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is known for her support of the temperance movement, even though her husband, Rutherford, actually banned alcohol from the White House?",
          "answer": "”Lemonade” Lucy Webb Hayes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Died shortly after her husband, Andrew Jackson, was elected.",
          "answer": "Rachel Donelson Jackson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Constantinople",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Two continents on which Constantinople resided.",
          "answer": [
            "Europe and Asia",
            "in either order",
            "Eurasia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Strategic strait it sat on, controlling access to the Black Sea.",
          "answer": "Bosporus or Bosphorus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second-largest Christian church in the world, based in Constantinople, which broke with Rome in 1054.",
          "answer": "Eastern Orthodox Catholic Church do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire that held its capital in Constantinople for a thousand years and was named for a previous name of the city.",
          "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "ArabcaliphatethatbesiegedConstantinopleintheeighthcenturyandwassucceededbytheAbbasids.",
          "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of Murad II, an Ottoman sultan who conquered the city in 1453.",
          "answer": "Mehmed the Conqueror or Mehmed II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inlet that served as an important harbor, crossed today by the Galata Bridge and centuries ago by a large defensive chain.",
          "answer": [
            "Golden Horn",
            "Halic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Palace that served as home to Ottoman sultans after its conquest.",
          "answer": [
            "Topkapi Palace",
            "the Seraglio"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Han Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Method of payment used to pay taxes in the Han Dynasty. Western ones are often made of gold and silver.",
          "answer": "coins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Philosophy that it embraced, whose namesake is the source of the Analects.",
          "answer": [
            "Confucianism",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty before the Han, the first to unify China.",
          "answer": "Qin Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Basis of Han leadership, the idea that the emperor had a divine right to rule.",
          "answer": "Mandate of Heaven"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom to the south where Han rule was briefly interrupted by the Trung sisters’ revolt.",
          "answer": "Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellion of peasants based in secret Taoist societies and put down by Cao Cao [tsao-tsao].",
          "answer": "Yellow Turban Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of strife that followed the fall of the Han dynasty and was described by one of the Four Great Classical Novels.",
          "answer": [
            "Three Kingdoms Period",
            "Romance of the Three Kingdoms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First capital of the Han Dynasty until it was moved to Luoyang; the site of modern-day Xi’an [shee-an].",
          "answer": "Chang’an"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was blamed for the shelling of Mainila, a false flag operation that ended a non-aggression pact. Less than a year after that war ended, aggression against this country resumed in the (20 pts)",
        "Continuation War. This country was defended by the Mannerheim line, from which soldiers tossed Molotov cocktails at the Red Army. The (10 pts)",
        "Soviet Union was expelled from the League of Nations in December 1939 after it invaded, for ten points, what Scandinavian country in the Winter War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Finland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man responded to criticism from hippies by noting that he was “killing fascists while [they] were in diapers.” In order to circumvent a two-term tenure limit, this man convinced his wife (20 pts)",
        "Lurleen to succeed him. This Independent Party candidate in the 1968 Presidential Election rose to fame after declaring a commitment to “segregation (10 pts)",
        "now, segregation tomorrow, and segregation forever” at a 1963 inaugural address. For ten points, name this governor who performed the “stand in the schoolhouse door” against the integration of the University of Alabama."
      ],
      "answer": "George Wallace"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To avoid paying damages, the orchestra for this event was relocated from the Hotel Biltmore to the Park Plaza. Reporter Carl Phillips was killed early in this event, which included Ray Collins’ panicked report of people jumping into the (20 pts)",
        "East River to escape black smoke. This event is memorialized with a three-legged statue in Woking, England and a ground-zero marker in Grovers Mill, (10 pts)",
        "New Jersey. Mercury Theater on the Air produced, for ten points, what 1938 radioplay by Orson Welles, based on a novel by H.G. Wells, which caused a mass panic of people who thought the Martian invasion was real?"
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Worlds radio broadcast"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to a possibly apocryphal story, this man fled his home when Michael VIII Palaiologos ordered the Venetian Quarter of Constantinople burned down. After one voyage, this man was allegedly captured at the Battle of Curzola by (20 pts)",
        "Genoans. During one trek, he traveled by camel to Hormuz before arriving at Shengdu. This man’s credibility was brought into question by historians who noticed that this man never wrote about (10 pts)",
        "footbinding, walls, or chopsticks. Kublai Khan was supposedly the patron of, for ten points, what Italian merchant who traveled to the Yuan Dynasty in China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Marco Polo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the aftermath of one battle at this location, a victorious Gallic force marched to Delphi under the command of Brennus. This location is bound to the north by the Gulf of Malia, and is named for the presence of (20 pts)",
        "hot springs nearby. Ephialtes [eff-ee-all-tees] showed an enemy commander a way to circumvent this location, where the army of (10 pts)",
        "Leonidas was then killed by Xerxes’ [zerk-zee’s] invading Persian army. For ten points, name this battle site where, in 480 BC, over three hundred Spartan soldiers were killed in a mountain pass."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thermopylae",
        "Battles of Thermopylae",
        "descriptions of the mountain pass at Thermopylae, prompting on partial answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A farm owned by this city’s first leader was turned into the Royal Botanic Garden by Lachlan Macquarie, who appointed “emancipists” to its government. Early in this city’s history, it was moved north to (20 pts)",
        "Port Jackson from the landing site of the HMS Endeavour, Botany Bay. This city’s harbor is home to a Jorn Utzon-designed building with sail-like (10 pts)",
        "shells, and it was founded as the capital of the British penal colony of New South Wales. For ten points, name this city with a notable opera house, the most populous in Australia."
      ],
      "answer": "Sydney"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s despair that “all that I have written seems like straw to me” led to an unfinished magnum opus. This man was more successful than a predecessor, Siger of Brabant, in claiming the doctrine of “double truth.” This thinker divided law into (20 pts)",
        "eternal, natural, human, and divine forms. This author defended the Christian religion from the “unbelievers” of Jews and Muslims in Summa contra Gentiles and synthesized (10 pts)",
        "Aristotelian philosophy with a Christian worldview in another work. For ten points, name this medieval Dominican friar, the author of Summa Theologica."
      ],
      "answer": "Saint Thomas Aquinas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The victory at this battle inspired a song that began “What’s the cause of this commotion, motion, motion...” and notes “Van is a used up man.” The winning side in this battle was reinforced by the Yellow Jacket militia, and the losing commander later blamed the (20 pts)",
        "Winnebagos for attacking too early. Joseph Daviess was killed in this battle while leading a counter-charge near (10 pts)",
        "Prophetstown. Tenskwatawa, the brother of Tecumseh, was defeated at, for ten points, what 1811 battle that coined an enduring nickname for William Henry Harrison?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Tippecanoe"
    }
  ]
}